There are 12 of them.
12 stadiums built in the four corners of Europe.
Conceived by the most daring architects and built by thousands of workers and engineers.
12 gigantic arenas selected to host matches for a global event,
the 2020 European Football Championship.
Embark on a unique tour of Europe to discover the most beautiful stadiums on the continent.
In this episode,
The match will pit Wembley Stadium in London, England against the Allianz Arena in Munich, Germany.
On one hand,
a 90,000-seat stadium with a retractable roof,
supported by a huge arch.
A stadium built in accordance with English traditions and a global benchmark in football.
Pelé nicknamed it the cathedral of football.
the football capital,
the heart of football.
And on the other hand,
an arena entirely dedicated to football
where the viewer is placed as close as possible to the action.
A stadium with an innovative design,
covered with an inflatable cushion skin,
capable of lighting up with a thousand lights.
To illuminate the facade,
We have a palette of 16 million colors,
And that applies to all the diamond shapes.
London and Munich,
The clash of two titans.
Let's begin our journey in England,
the homeland of football.
About ten kilometers from central London,
Wembley Stadium stands prominently,
inaugurated in 2007 and completely rebuilt on the site of the old enclosure.
Wembley,
a legendary stadium for an entire people.
A reputation that goes far beyond borders and has reached a global dimension.
Simon Inglis is a historian and leading expert on British football.
He has written several books on the origins of this temple of football.
Wembley Stadium exists because, after the First World War,
Great Britain wanted to organize a large exhibition to celebrate peace and also to let the world know that its colonial adventure was still in full swing.
It was really complicated to raise the necessary funds,
to interest the British public and investors.
And in 1921,
they said to themselves,
Let's put a stadium here.
Let's build a national stadium.
There was this notion that England needed a stadium befitting the Empire.
And obviously,
They called it the Empire Stadium.
Built in barely a year,
At the time, this stadium was the largest in the world.
capable of accommodating up to 127,000 standing spectators.
On the day of its inauguration,
The stadium is packed.
Tens of thousands of ticketless fans invade the pitch.
They have come to attend the most anticipated match of the year.
the FA Cup final,
the English Cup (football).
Over the decades,
The Empire Stadium will set the rhythm of British life.
The country's biggest events are held there.
The 1948 Olympic Games and especially the 1966 FIFA World Cup.
The 1966 World Cup,
the only time...
The only time England,
the so-called home of football,
actually wins the World Cup.
And what's more,
It happens at home.
And that,
Nothing can take it away from us.
For my generation,
This is a key date in our lives.
And we associate that with Wembley.
Wembley. It's part of our collective memory.
From the 1990s onwards,
The stadium's glory days are numbered.
The leaders of the English Football Association want a more modern stadium.
Five different cities have submitted bids to replace Wembley.
Wembley,
obviously,
then Bradford,
Sheffield,
Manchester and Birmingham.
They all made an offer to host the new national stadium.
For the first time since the 1920s,
Wembley had to justify its importance to the entire nation.
And that's what she did.
The city of Wembley won the tender.
Especially because the football association saw only Wembley as a suitable venue for England team matches and cup finals.
it's necessary
It had to be in London.
So this is it,
on the very site of the former Wembley stadium,
that the new enclosure now stands.
A huge stadium with a capacity of 90,000,
four times higher than the old arena and covering twice the area.
It is the largest stadium in the country and one of the largest covered stadiums in the world.
Access to the stands is via 36 entrances distributed all around the stadium.
The facilities and services offered to supporters reflect the high standards of this football temple.
excessive.
No fewer than 98 kitchens supply the 688 fast food and beverage kiosks.
There are about ten restaurants present.
including some reserved exclusively for the 17,500 privileged members of the highly selective Club Wembley.
The Royal family also has its own private entrances and elevators to watch matches from the Royal Box.
But to reach such an extreme,
The architects at Foster & Partners had to overcome many challenges.
The first was to design a modern venue while preserving its extraordinary heritage.
The most famous feature of the old stadium,
It was his two masterful towers at the entrance.
They had been the symbol of English football history for 80 years and their destruction shook the entire British people.
When we started studying design,
We were standing in front of a 75-year-old national monument with its two towers as symbols.
They were approximately 35 meters tall.
And when we wondered if we could keep them,
We realized that the new stadium was really too big.
We were forced to move them or even demolish them.
One of the biggest challenges has been replacing this national icon.
We needed something visually powerful.
It was while searching for a way to support the colossal weight of the roof that the architects came up with the idea of ​​the element that might be able to replace the two towers in the hearts of the English.
We studied the idea of ​​an arch extending over the roof.
So we had to decide how to support the roof using the arch.
And we were rather intrigued by the idea of ​​diagonal cables.
And these cables that descend from the arch form a structure.
If we look at it from a distance,
It looks like a crown.
a tiara.
We thought it would create a very strong image of the stadium.
The engineers will then create a steel structure 315 meters long and 135 meters high.
An immense arch composed of 42 segments, each 7.5 meters in diameter and 10.4 meters long.
They first assembled all the elements on the ground,
then fixed the two attachment points to the ground on each side of the arch.
They then rotated the 1700-tonne arch over the enclosure.
For architects and engineers,
Assembling and installing the arch was one of the most delicate stages in the construction of the stadium.
The arch was erected on the site.
on the ground,
for 10 months,
then lifted above the lawn for 6 weeks,
in 3 steps.
First, at 30 degrees above the ground.
60 degrees,
100 degrees and finally 112 degrees.
All of this was monitored and controlled by computer 24 hours a day to ensure that all connections were acting as expected.
Once the arch is held in position,
inclined at 112 degrees,
A huge metal ring, one kilometer long, was placed around the perimeter wall.
Starting from this metal ring,
A series of beams were constructed above the stadium stands to form the roof structure.
During this construction phase,
Temporary towers were erected to hold the metal beams above the void.
Once the roof is finished,
The weight of the roof beams was transferred to the arch by means of a series of cables stretched between the arch and the northern part of the roof.
In the end,
The arch supports the entire weight of the northern part of the roof and also 60%
of the weight of the southern part.
The 40%
the remaining weight is supported by the main structure of the enclosure.
The arch remains in permanent balance thanks to the balancing action between the north and south parts of the roof.
A technical feat that makes it possible to avoid the use of support pillars inside the stadium.
As an architect,
I really appreciate the collaborative work that has been done between our teams and that of the other firm.
I think it's a really complex work.
First of all,
stands that are fixed,
an arch that would fall if it weren't for the roof to keep it balanced,
and a roof that is supported by the arch,
which is itself under tension.
A roof whose fixed sections protect the spectators,
but which is also equipped with immovable elements to ensure safety.
I think there is a real harmony that is quite exceptional.
Originally,
the stadium was known for its two towers.
And now,
130 meters wide,
You can actually see it from over 60 kilometers away.
SO,
not only does it become a new symbol of the stadium,
but it's something instantly recognizable.
No other stadium in the world has that.
As with Wembley Stadium in London,
The distinctive architecture of a stadium can transform certain buildings into emblems of an entire city.
One of the most striking examples is in Germany,
in Munich,
capital of Bavaria.
The city is home to one of the most beautiful stadiums in the world,
the Allianz Arena.
Renowned for its exceptional architecture and its dazzling white exterior,
It is nicknamed the inflatable boat.
This stadium was built in 2005 to house the city's two clubs.
TSV 1860 and FC Bayern.
Since 2017,
It is the exclusive property of FC Bayern Munich.
the most decorated club in the country and one of the biggest in Europe with 5 Champions League titles to its credit.
But to build a new stadium north of Munich,
Many challenges had to be overcome.
The first,
to convince local authorities of the need for a temple entirely dedicated to football.
In the 1990s,
The two federations already wanted to build a new football stadium in Munich.
At the time,
They were playing at the Olympia stadium.
That is to say, in a stadium that is not a football stadium,
but something completely different.
A huge stadium,
very open.
It has a larger area and surrounds the football pitch,
There is a 400-meter athletics track.
The spectators are therefore very far removed from the game.
It is also a stadium with only one row of stands,
That is to say, there is a very flat plane.
So we are even further removed from the game.
The distance between the spectators,
The playing field and the players are significantly more important.
And it was from this observation that we had the idea of ​​building a real football stadium north of Munich, and not an Olympic stadium.
In October 2001,
Munich residents vote in favor of a new football stadium.
despite the reluctance of the city council, which would prefer to renovate the old Olympic stadium.
The construction project began in October 2002 and lasted two and a half years.
At the time,
The architects and engineers had to overcome many challenges.
The first of them,
the location chosen for its construction.
Located in the north of Munich,
between the airport and the city center,
The building is wedged between a railway line and a motorway.
It was in this precise location that it was necessary to build not only a 171,000 m² stadium,
but also a giant car park for spectators.
The construction costs will be borne by the two clubs in the city.
At the head of this monument, which has become one of the city's emblems,
Jürgen Muth,
stadium manager.
This is one of the first stages that gave great importance to architecture.
We worked with world-renowned architects,
Jacques Herzog and Pierre de Meuron,
who did not simply build a stadium out of concrete and steel,
but above all a kind of envelope.
This stadium has been featured on magazine covers.
And today,
We are proud to see that the architects,
but also the public attending the European Championship or fans from all over the world who come to Munich just to visit this building.
According to Robert Hossel,
project manager of the Allianz Arena,
This stadium was not to resemble any other.
We absolutely did not want to turn this roof and facade into a classical building.
The idea,
The goal was to create a curved object.
all curved,
which in a way closes in on itself.
This geometry can therefore be found almost everywhere.
Even on the facade with its cushions,
which was placed somewhat like a cocoon,
like a skin.
NOW,
This facade and roof make this building a true object.
An extraordinary object,
symbol of a new era in stadium design.
To achieve such an architectural feat,
The engineers will propose an original material that has already proven its worth in construction.
but until now never used for a football stadium.
Ethylene tetrafluoroethylene,
code name
ETFE.
This plastic material can be stretched into a film.
By layering them,
This creates pockets that can be inflated to form cushions.
The Alliance Arena envelope is therefore composed of exactly
2742 plastic inflatable cushions.
The assembly took 9 months of work.
A giant puzzle where each diamond-shaped piece must fit perfectly with the others.
Each cushion measures on average 6 meters by 3 meters and its plastic casing does not exceed
0.25 mm thick.
With a density of barely 350 grams per square meter,
The cushion is ultra-light but very durable.
It can support up to 400 times its own weight.
The use of ETFE therefore considerably reduces the load on the roof structure.
Tobias Sieber is the stadium maintenance manager.
He takes us into the bowels of the Allianz Arena to reveal the secrets of its gigantic inflatable facade.
Each cushion is constantly maintained under a pressure of 300 pascals.
This pressure is generated by four air supply devices.
The air is distributed through a very complex network of ducts that measures several kilometers.
On the roof,
There are sensors.
which measure wind intensity and snow depth.
This information is sent to the air supply system, which then automatically adjusts the pressure sent to the cushions.
The pressure can reach up to 800 pascals and the cushions can support the weight of one meter of snow without any problem.
Of course,
Holes may form in the cushions.
But thanks to the low pressure inside,
You can have a hole of 5 to 10 cm without the cushion deforming and eventually collapsing.
Regularly,
Stadium technicians access the roof to carry out inspection and maintenance visits.
This material is really very strong.
You can sit on it and even lie down on it.
It holds up perfectly.
That's great.
Regularly,
We come to check for the presence of holes and we repair them.
During the design of the stadium...
The engineers had to overcome another challenge.
What should be done in case of a complete shutdown of the ventilation system?
In case of a ventilation system failure...
Large quantities of water could accumulate on the roof.
This would potentially represent several hundred tons that the roof would have to support.
And the cushions could very well collapse under the weight of all that rain.
An ingenious drainage system was then devised to prevent the roof from collapsing under the weight of the water.
Each roof cushion is equipped with a long hollow tube.
In the event of a failure of the emergency ventilation systems,
The cushions will deflate and water will then begin to fill the bottom.
But the liquid cannot accumulate in large quantities,
because it is gradually evacuated through the tubes.
This ingenious system makes it possible to considerably reduce the load on the roof structure.
Apart from the rain,
The heat of the sun is another threat to the roof of the Allianz Arrila.
Because of its permeability to UV light,
The TFE allows a large amount of light and energy to pass through, which accumulates under the roof.
It's a bit like a greenhouse effect where it's much hotter inside than outside.
It can reach up to 80 or 90 degrees in summer.
To regulate the temperature,
The engineers therefore created several ventilation openings.
which allow heat to dissipate.
They are evenly distributed around the outer ring of the roof.
Despite the heat,
Sunlight is a determining factor in the design of a stadium.
The architects must orient the stadium so that the players and spectators do not have the sun in their eyes during a match.
They also need to think about the lawn, which needs light to grow.
To flood the stadium's grass with sunlight,
The architects of the Alliance Arena came up with the idea of ​​using two types of cushions at the roof level.
The cushions located to the north and northeast of the stadium,
little exposure to the sun,
are tinted white in order to reflect as much light as possible and reduce heat under the roof.
Those located to the south and southwest of the stadium,
very exposed to the sun
They are transparent to allow the penetration of solar radiation necessary for the proper growth of the grass.
During matches,
Large grey curtains are drawn under these transparent cushions to limit the sun on the playing field.
In London too,
The architects had to work around the sun.
They had to maintain the east-west orientation of the pitch in order to preserve the soul of the old Wembley and ensure that on the day of the FA Cup final,
The lawn is in full sun.
This orientation is ideal for avoiding shaded areas during the broadcast of the match and provides maximum sunlight to the pitch.
But the International Federation of Football requires that a roof be placed over all seats during international competitions.
A new constraint for architects to take into account.
We are faced with this kind of dilemma.
FIFA requires us to cover all the seats in the stadium.
But since the stadium has 90,000 seats and the stands are so high,
This means that the opening in the middle of the roof would be very small.
So the lawn would die.
To maximize the amount of light on the lawn,
The engineers devised a clever system of retractable and stackable panels.
The aluminum roof is divided into 7 movable panels.
3 panels located on the east side,
3 on the west side and a huge sign to the south.
The opening always starts with the first 2 panels from the bottom.
As we reverse,
these will draw the latter into their race
3rd panel.
The same process takes place on the west side.
Finally,
The largest panel located to the south can also be removed.
Once opened,
The entire surface of the lawn is thus bathed in sunlight.
Ian Stevenson is in charge of the roofing.
We find him again at the moment the roof is opened.
Okay Dave,
The start-up checks are carried out to the west.
The hatches are closed.
The signs are ready when you're ready.
I repeat,
Ready when you're ready.
Okay,
well received.
We are beginning to open the S section of the roof.
I repeat.
Opening of section S of the roof,
finished.
Well received.
The alarm sounds to indicate that the systems are running and that the roof is retracting.
Here we go.
So we're just going to head towards the drive unit and we're just going to observe and monitor the retracting roof.
All the panels at once.
There,
This is the widest panel on the east side.
the top panel number 1,
which arrives in its final position.
Those sensors,
For example,
are located on the tracks.
These sensors allow the movement to be triggered or stopped.
They are coordinated with the central computer which controls the roof and thus commands its stopping in the final position.
Thanks to all these sensors,
The teams in the control room can track in real time the speed and position of each part of the moving roof.
Here,
We can see that there are different alarms and warning lights.
They activate when there is a problem with any part of the roof.
If there is something blocking it,
if there is a strong gust of wind that could misalign the roof,
The roof stops.
And that,
We'll see it instantly on this screen.
It will flash.
And I need to understand what the lights or alarms indicate.
then manage the problem and restart the opening or closing of the roof depending on what we are doing.
In the end,
No less than 57 minutes are needed to move the panels on the east and west sides and 17 minutes for the south panel.
If the roof protects against inclement weather and sun,
It also plays an unexpected but well-known role for architects.
It contributes to the propagation of sound.
Old Wembley was renowned worldwide for its deafening atmosphere, particularly the roar of the fans when the players entered the pitch.
It was called the Wembley Raw.
One of the most amazing things about old Wembley,
It was the sound swirling inside the enclosure.
Hamden Park has something very similar,
called the Hamden Roar.
And that simply comes down to the fact that,
when you have 100,000...
With people in the stands, the acoustics bounced everywhere, and in 1963 they installed roofs to close off the stadium, which increased the noise level. It was a super noisy place, and that really helps during a football match.
To recreate this very special atmosphere,
The architects analyzed the behavior of sound in the old Wembley stadium.
The results allowed them to improve the acoustics inside the new venue.
We see some stadiums that have spaces between the back of the stands and the roof.
If there is a space,
The sound exits through this space.
The space was closed off.
A strip of glass was put all around the stadium.
And like that,
The sound really fills the entire interior.
inside the enclosure and reverberates throughout the stadium.
So we get an echo.
Spectators feel the atmosphere much more because the sound bounces off the roof and glass walls at the back of the stands and comes back onto the pitch into the players' ears.
They can also hear the lower stand.
We realized that the sounds from the lower stands reverberate throughout the stadium.
but they also arrive directly at lawn level.
So when you have a very large lower stand,
That's what players hear most often.
It makes them feel better and that's important for them.
It's a real success.
Even when Wembley is not completely full,
We know that the atmosphere is as it was in the past,
and even better, in fact.
The viewers enjoy a better quality experience.
They come and are transported into a unique experience.
Create an atmosphere,
to bring the fans as close to the action as possible,
has become a trademark and a guarantee of quality for the biggest football stadiums.
For the architects at Herzog & de Meuron,
These elements were a priority from the very beginning of the stadium's design.
The instruction for the construction of the Allianz Arena was to create a stadium specifically designed for football.
where fans are in direct contact with the players.
There can even be genuine interaction during the match.
The spectators are very close to the playing field.
There are three levels of seating,
The fans really dominate the game and the stadium interior is more compact.
more focused on the football match.
To bring the audience as close to the action as possible,
The architects meticulously worked on the curvature of the enclosure and the layout of the stands.
The challenge was to guarantee each visitor the best visibility and an unobstructed view from any point in the stands.
For that,
The architects had to ensure that a spectator could see action on the field without being obstructed by the head of the person sitting in front of him.
This spectator's line of sight should not be obstructed by the head of the person in front of him.
The same applies to the downstairs neighbor.
whose line of sight should not be disturbed by its neighbor below.
The architects therefore defined a minimum distance to be maintained between the lines of sight of the spectators.
in order to guarantee them maximum visual comfort.
The greater this distance,
The better the visibility.
So,
Spectators in the lower stands of the Alliance Arena have a line of sight separated by an average of 10 cm.
While on the intermediate stand,
The visibility lines are spaced 9 cm apart.
In the upper tier,
they are separated by on average
8 cm.
To offer greater visibility to spectators in the upper tier,
The architects did not hesitate to tilt the grandstand to its maximum angle.
that is, 34 degrees as permitted by regulations.
But the atmosphere of a sporting event is not only created during the match itself.
It begins as soon as the public arrives near the stadium.
To accommodate the 70,000 fans,
The architects of the Alliance Arena envisioned a huge esplanade overlooking a parking lot.
The challenge was enormous because we had to create 11,000 spaces for what was going to be the largest covered car park in Europe.
in a stadium.
Rather than building a huge, invisible underground car park beneath the stadium,
The architects therefore designed an esplanade surrounding the enclosure, under which different levels were built to accommodate vehicles.
600 meters long and 134 meters wide,
The esplanade rises to a height of 12 meters and then descends slightly to the level of the second floor of the stadium.
This brilliant idea completely transformed spectator access to the stadium.
Like a modern-day cathedral,
The enclosure gradually reveals itself to them as their hatred intensifies.
On match days,
The Esplanade is where it all begins.
It must be a welcoming place,
so that the suspense gradually builds among the fans,
until the moment they all find themselves inside the stadium to watch a good football match.
The Esplanade offers a place where the staging can begin.
The Allianz Arena needs the esplanade,
and the esplanade is the backdrop for the stadium and the game.
In this game of staging,
The architects thought big and also devised an ingenious lighting system.
Undoubtedly the one that made the Allianz Arena famous throughout the world.
What's special about this stadium,
That's because it was the headquarters of two football clubs.
Two clubs that therefore have different identities,
different fans.
Therefore, a stadium was needed that would serve as an identifying element for both clubs.
It was a big challenge not to build a neutral stadium.
So I had the idea to solve this problem,
these different identities,
using colored lights.
That is to say, to build a stadium which,
a bit like a chameleon,
can change identity depending on the team that is playing.
Lyon 1860 or FC Bayern?
To create this play of light,
The engineers placed a series of panels composed of 285 red LEDs at the base of each cushion.
green and yellow which,
once mixed,
can provide a palette of 16 million colors.
Thanks to its transparency characteristics,
The TFE allows light to pass through and diffuses it outwards.
giving the cushion a perfectly uniform color.
In total,
300,000 LEDs illuminate all the cushions surrounding the facade of the Alliance Arena.
Since the departure of the TSV 1860,
The arena now shines in red, the colours of FC Bayern Munich.
Thanks to the shape of the cushions and the lighting,
It is possible to recreate all sorts of patterns,
including the club's famous logo,
which proudly displays the blue and white diamonds of the Bavarian flag.
At the helm of this multicolored game,
Christian Oussalman,
technical director of the arena.
We are in the Alliance Arena control center.
the nerve center.
This is where we can control everything.
including the facade.
On World Diabetes Day,
We illuminate it in blue.
During the week,
when there is no match,
We activate an animation that alternates between red and white every three minutes.
We can also set up special events like during Independence Day with the Stars and Stripes.
In green for St. Patrick's Day.
Or in the colours of Christopher Street Day.
Or even in orange for the King of Holland's holiday.
In general,
for international teams,
The facade is illuminated in white.
But you can also display the colors of the national flag.
Every night of the year,
The Alliance Arena shines like a beacon in the middle of the Bavarian plain.
The landscape here is very open.
because it is a motorway junction.
And we wanted to lay a foundation here for Munich,
at its main entrance,
north of the city.
This luminous object dominates the landscape.
1000 kilometers away,
Another lighthouse ignites the London suburbs.
Can the arch at Wembley Stadium also put on its colorful clothes?
We made the decision to install a system to light up the arch when night falls.
And since the lights are hidden within the structure,
They glow from within and you never see the light source.
It really gives it an extra special feature.
When you put lights in the stadium,
It becomes like jewels that shine inside this enormous structure.
And it can be seen from very far away.
We thought it would become a very powerful image for the stadium.
And to change the lights hidden in the arch,
The engineers envisioned a gondola capable of moving inside the structure itself.
There,
You can see that we've already removed one light.
And then,
These are the supports.
We removed a light because the bulb burned out.
And so,
next week,
We're going to go back up to fix it.
Jerry Mortimer is in charge of maintenance work.
With each crossing,
He is always impressed by the sheer size of the structure.
Look at its size.
Even there,
on the rail,
in the gondola,
I am standing.
There is still room for a second person above my head.
And you have 2m under the gondola and therefore 2m above the gondola.
That's huge.
When we are around the stadium,
It's something we don't really realize.
the impressive size of the item.
The arch is 7.5 meters in diameter.
We take a Eurostar and we can get it through.
That's considerable.
Right now,
We are at the highest point of the Ark.
We're higher than the London Eye.
And we're right in the middle.
That ring there,
It is the only ring that does not have a light.
With this new stadium,
The British architects have succeeded in their gamble.
To create a temple of modern football,
while preserving the tradition and soul of the old Wembley.
Working on this stadium has truly been a unique experience.
I was so proud when it opened.
I am a sports fan.
I wanted to be involved in this project from the very beginning.
And I created something that allows anyone to come and have a unique experience.
The Alliance Arena, meanwhile, has become a powerful symbol for an entire city.
a region,
or even a country.
Munich is a very important city for us.
And we are always very happy to be able to carry out a project that is so important for the city.
which has such a decisive effect on her and can transform her.
This had already happened to us several times.
but this one belongs to another category,
completely separate.
This is an exception.
a bit like the Tate Monaco.
modern in London or the Hamburg Philharmonie.
This kind of opportunity doesn't come around all the time.
These are rare opportunities that must be seized.
Due to their unique architecture,
The Alliance Arena and Wembley are now benchmarks in stadium construction.
But what the architects have also achieved,
It's about recreating visual atmospheres,
bright and loud displays that provide fans with an unforgettable experience.